Frank Knox Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Frank Knox Papers 1898-1954
MSS28845
Knox, Frank, 1874-1944
2,800 items
12 containers plus 7 oversize
5.4 linear feet
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Newspaper editor and publisher, and U.S. secretary of the navy. Correspondence, diaries, speeches and writings, newspaper clippings, scrapbooks, and miscellany relating to Knox's service in the Spanish-American War and World War I, his work as editor and publisher, 1936 campaign for vice president, and stint as secretary of the navy. Includes papers of his wife, Annie Reid Knox.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Chiang, Kai-shek, 1887-1975--Correspondence.; Coolidge, Calvin, 1872-1933--Correspondence.; Ford, Henry, 1863-1947--Correspondence.; Forrestal, James, 1892-1949--Correspondence.; Frankfurter, Felix, 1882-1965--Correspondence.; Hull, Cordell, 1871-1955--Correspondence.; Ickes, Harold L. (Harold LeClair), 1874-1952--Correspondence.; Knox, Annie Reid, 1876-1958. Annie Reid Knox papers. 1936-1954.; Knox, Frank, 1874-1944.; Lippmann, Walter, 1889-1974--Correspondence.; Marshall, George C. (George Catlett), 1880-1959--Correspondence.; Muehling, John Adam, 1862-1944--Correspondence.; Roosevelt, Franklin D. (Franklin Delano), 1882-1945--Correspondence.; Roosevelt, Theodore, 1858-1919--Correspondence.; Vandenberg, Arthur H. (Arthur Hendrick), 1884-1951--Correspondence.; White, William Allen, 1868-1944--Correspondence.; Willkie, Wendell L. (Wendell Lewis), 1892-1944--Correspondence.
Organizations
Republican Party (U.S.: 1854- ); United States. Army. Volunteer Cavalry, 1st.; United States. Navy Department.
Subjects
American newspapers--Illinois--Chicago.; Spanish-American War, 1898.; Vice-Presidential candidates--United States--1936.; World War, 1914-1918.
Places
United States--Politics and government--1901-1953.
Titles
Chicago Daily News.
Occupations
Cabinet officers.; Newspaper editors.; Publishers.
Acquisition Information
The papers of Frank Knox, newspaper editor and publisher and and U.S. secretary of the navy, were given to the Library of Congress by his wife, Annie Reid Knox, 1950-1954.
Transfers
Photographs have been transferred to the Prints and Photographs Division where they are identified as part of the Frank Knox Papers.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of Frank Knox are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1874, Jan. 1 Born, Boston, Mass.
1881 Moved to Grand Rapids, Mich.
1898 A.B., Alma College, Alma, Mich. Private in “Rough Rider” regiment of Leonard Wood and Theodore Roosevelt
1890 Married Annie Reid
1898 Reporter, Grand Rapids Herald
1902 With John Adam Muehling purchased the Lake Superior Journal, Sault Ste. Marie, Mich.
1912 Sold Lake Superior Journal and started the Manchester Union and Leader. Manchester, N.H.
1917 1918 Artillery officer with American Expeditionary Force in France
1928 Became publisher of Boston American for William Randolph Hearst
1929 Appointed general manager for all Hearst newspapers
1931 Resigned from Hearst organization
1932 Purchased with Theodore Ellis the Chicago Daily News
1933 Became sole owner of the Chicago Daily News
1936 Nominated and campaigned as Republican vice-presidential candidate
1940 Appointed secretary of the navy
1944, Apr. 28 Died, Washington, D.C.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Frank Knox (1877-1944) span the years 1898-1954. The collection consists mainly of family and special correspondence, some general correspondence, Knox's speeches and writings, correspondence and speeches of his wife, Annie Reid Knox, and a clippings file. Additional papers donated by Annie Reid Knox document the establishment of the Frank Knox Memorial Fellowship at Harvard University. The Knox Papers are strongest for his role in politics and government service; they contain little material relating to his career as a publisher. The collection is organized into eight series: Diaries, Family Correspondence, General Correspondence, Special Correspondence, Speeches and Writings, Annie Reid Knox File, Miscellany, and Oversize.
The Family Correspondence reflects Knox's service as a private in the Rough Riders regiment in the Spanish-American War and his World War I service as an artillery officer. The letters to his wife in the 1930s and 1940s provide insights into the development of his public career. A Special Correspondence file of letters with Theodore Roosevelt documents Knox's support of Roosevelt's political ambitions from 1911 through 1918.
The General Correspondence extends from 1917 through 1944, but the bulk of the material covers Knox's service as secretary of the navy. This series includes letters with many prominent public figures such as Calvin Coolidge, Henry Ford, James Forrestal, Felix Frankfurter, Cordell Hull, Chiang Kai-shek, Harold L. Ickes, Walter Lippmann, George Marshall, John Adam Muehling, Franklin D. Roosevelt, Arthur H. Vandenberg, William Allen White, Wendell Willkie.
Knox's Speeches and Writings cover the major addresses he delivered from the late 1930s through his tenure as secretary of the navy. The writings include a series of editorials he wrote from 1934 to 1940 while he was publisher and editor of the Chicago Daily News. The clippings file contains rather extensive coverage of Knox's campaign as Republican vice-presidential candidate in 1936.
Arrangement of the Papers
This collection is arranged in eight series:
Diaries, 1898-1944
Family Correspondence, 1898-1944
General Correspondence, 1917-1944
Special Correspondence, 1911-1943
Speeches and Writings, 1914-1944
Annie Reid Knox File, 1936-1954
Miscellany
Oversize
Container List
- Diaries, 1898-1944 (Box 1)
  Secretary of the navy logbook, desk calendar for 1943, record book of lunches and dinners, calendar of Knox's life compiled by Annie Reid Knox, and incomplete diary.
  Arranged chronologically.
  - Itinerary, Sept. 1943 (Box 1)
  - Flight logbook, 1940-1944 (Box 1)
  - Daybook, 1943 (Box 1)
  - Record book of dinners, 1940-1942 (Box 1)
  - Record book of life of Frank Knox Diary, 7, 13, 28 May 1941 (Box 1)
- Family Correspondence, 1898-1944 (Box 2-3)
  Correspondence with parents and with Annie Reid Knox.
  - Frank Knox to parents 1898-1921 (Box 2)
  - Frank Knox to Annie Reid Knox (with some replies) (Box 2)
    - 1910-1932, (5 folders) (Box 2)
    - 1933-1944, (6 folders) (Box 3)
- General Correspondence, 1917-1944 (Box 4)
  Letters sent and received.
  - 1917-1944, (8 folders) (Box 4)
- Special Correspondence, 1911-1943 (Box 5)
  Correspondence with John Adam Muehling and Theodore Roosevelt.
  Arranged by name of correspondent and thereunder chronologically.
  - John Adam Muehling, 1918, 1943 (Box 5)
  - Theodore Roosevelt, 1911-1918 (Box 5)
- Speeches and Writings, 1914-1944 (Box 5-7)
  Texts of most speeches delivered by Knox between 1934 and 1944 and writings.
  Organized into speeches and writings and therein chronologically.
  - Speeches (Box 5)
    - Des Moines, Iowa, 12 Feb. 1934 (Box 5)
    - Faculty Forum Group, University of Illinois, Champagne-Urbana, Ill., 4 Apr. 1935 (Box 5)
    - Mortgage Bankers Association, Chicago, Ill., 5 Oct. 1935 (Box 5)
    - Republican Women's Club, 6 Nov. 1935 (Box 5)
    - Newspaper editors, 18 Nov. 1935 (Box 5)
    - Irvington Republican Club, 18 Nov. 1935 (Box 5)
    - Nebraska Republican Rally, Kearney, Neb., 22 Nov. 1935 (Box 5)
    - Associated Business Papers, New York City, 2 Dec. 1935 (Box 5)
    - Worcester Republican Club, Worcester, Ohio, 13 Dec. 1935 (Box 5)
    - Ohio Republican Editorial Association, 27 Dec. 1935 (Box 5)
    - North Dakota Press Association, 10 Jan. 1936 (Box 5)
    - Annual celebration of Le jour de Saints Barbe, 4 Dec. 1937 (Box 5)
    - National Association Legions of Honor, Cleveland, Ohio, 13 Apr. 1940 (Box 5)
    - Des Moines Economic Club, Des Moines, Iowa, 17 Apr. 1940 (Box 5)
    - Naval supplemental estimates for 1941, 18 July 1940 (Box 5)
    - Naval aircraft in national defense, 19 July 1940 (Box 5)
    - Editor and Publisher, 27 July 1940 (Box 5)
    - United States Navy, Aug. 1940 (Box 5)
    - Labor requirements of the navy, 2 Aug. 1940 (Box 5)
    - Broadcast on CBS, 4 Aug. 1940 (Box 5)
    - Navy policy on enlisting recruits, 7 Aug. 1940 (Box 5)
    - Overtime for navy labor, 8 Aug. 1940 (Box 5)
    - Conscription, 14 Aug. 1940 (Box 5)
    - Naval reserve aviation bases, 14 Aug. 1940 (Box 5)
    - Navy draft, 25 Sept. 1940 (Box 5)
    - Graduates of the National Police Academy, 5 Oct. 1940 (Box 5)
    - Press release on active duty of reserve, 5 Oct. 1940 (Box 5)
    - New York Herald Tribune Forum, 22 Oct. 1940 (Box 5)
    - “What Lies Ahead?,” 22 Oct. 1940 (Box 5)
    - Naval Council of Illinois, 26 Oct. 1940 (Box 5)
    - Radio address, Navy Day Program, 28 Oct. 1940 (Box 5)
    - Training for two-ocean navy, 30 Oct. 1940 (Box 5)
    - American Legion, 11 Nov. 1940 (Box 5)
    - New England Council, 14 Nov. 1940 (Box 5)
    - Editorial in Louisville Courier Journal, 17 Nov. 1940 (Box 5)
    - Schedule of wages, 19 Dec. 1940 (Box 5)
    - Christmas greetings on Mutual Network, 22 Dec. 1940 (Box 5)
    - Editorial in Chicago Daily News, Jan. 1941 (Box 5)
    - Statement before House Committee on Foreign Affairs, 17 Jan. 1941 (Box 5)
    - Canadian Society of New York, 18 Jan. 1941 (Box 5)
    - Radio address, “The Navy and the American People,” 21 Jan. 1941 (Box 5)
    - General Assembly of State Governments, 22 Jan. 1941 (Box 6)
    - State Street Council of Chicago, Chicago, Ill., 30 Jan. 1941 (Box 6)
    - Statement before Senate Committee on Foreign Relations, 30 Jan. 1941 (Box 6)
    - Graduates of United States Naval Academy, Annapolis, Md., 7 Feb. 1941 (Box 6)
    - “Naval News and National Defense,” 19 Feb. 1941 (Box 6)
    - VFW program on Mutual Network, 20 Feb. 1941 (Box 6)
    - Suggested outline of statement for “En Marcha,” 20 Feb. 1941 (Box 6)
    - United States Conference of Mayors, 20 Feb. 1941 (Box 6)
    - Hibernian Society of Baltimore, Md., 17 Mar. 1941 (Box 6)
    - Article, “Ships, Men, and Bases,” 5 Apr. 1941 (Box 6)
    - Lend-lease ships, 7 Apr. 1941 (Box 6)
    - Commissioning of North Carolina, 10 Apr. 1941 (Box 6)
    - Statement to United States Senate Committee to Investigate National Defense, 17 Apr. 1941 (Box 6)
    - American Newspaper Publishers Association, 24 Apr. 1941 (Box 6)
    - American Society of Military Engineers, 12 May 1941 (Box 6)
    - Graduation at Naval War College, 16 May 1941 (Box 6)
    - Society of Naval Engineers and Architects, 23 May 1941 (Box 6)
    - Remarks at Conference of Shipbuilders and Manufacturers, 3 June 1941 (Box 6)
    - Speech on CBC, 16 June 1941 (Box 6)
    - Governors Conference, 30 June 1941 (Box 6)
    - Statement to press, 12 July 1941 (Box 6)
    - American Legion, 15 Sept. 1941 (Box 6)
    - Pratt-Whitney employees, 22 Sept. 1941 (Box 6)
    - Launching of Massachusetts, 23 Sept. 1941 (Box 6)
    - Press directive concerning Knox's remarks at conference of navy public relations officers, 26 Sept. 1941 (Box 6)
    - American Bar Association, 1 Oct. 1941 (Box 6)
    - “The Significance of National Safety,” 8 Oct. 1941 (Box 6)
    - Statement at awards ceremony, 24 Oct. 1941 (Box 6)
    - Naval and Total Defense Day Luncheon, 27 Oct. 1941 (Box 6)
    - Statement concerning release of information on Kearney, 29 Oct. 1941 (Box 6)
    - Notes for secretary's press conference, 5 Nov. 1941 (Box 6)
    - Press conference question, 11 Nov. 1941 (Box 6)
    - Statement on American Red Cross, 11 Nov. 1941 (Box 6)
    - Providence, R.I., Chamber of Commerce, 11 Nov. 1941 (Box 6)
    - Speech on NBC, 15 Nov. 1941 (Box 6)
    - Launching of Indiana, 21 Nov. 1941 (Box 6)
    - Notes for secretary's press conference, 3 Dec. 1941 (Box 6)
    - Report on conduct of personnel during Pearl Harbor attack, 15 Dec. 1941 (Box 6)
    - Graduation of United States Naval Academy, Annapolis, Md., 19 Dec. 1941 (Box 6)
    - Proposed press release, 21 Dec. 1941 (Box 6)
    - United States Conference of Mayors, 17 Jan. 1942 (Box 6)
    - Chicago Association of Commerce, 28 Jan. 1942 (Box 6)
    - Launching of Alabama, 16 Feb. 1942 (Box 6)
    - Navy Relief Society dinner, 24 Feb. 1942 (Box 6)
    - Inter-American Defense Board, 30 Mar. 1942 (Box 6)
    - Released letters on forty-hour work week, 14 Apr. 1942 (Box 6)
    - Statement before Naval Affairs Committee, House of Representatives, 14 Apr. 1942 (Box 6)
    - Navy Relief Society, 4 May 1942 (Box 6)
    - Fore River Division, 15 May 1942 (Box 6)
    - Graduation speech, Naval War College, 6 June 1942 (Box 6)
    - Harvard commencement, Cambridge, Mass., 11 June 1942 (Box 6)
    - Boston Garden, Boston, Mass., 14 June 1942 (Box 6)
    - Navy war bond campaign, 24 July 1942 (Box 6)
    - Graduation at National Police Academy, 25 July 1942 (Box 6)
    - Labor Day statement, 6 Sept. 1942 (Box 6)
    - American Legion, 19 Sept. 1942 (Box 6)
    - Shore establishments dinner, 22 Oct. 1942 (Box 6)
    - Navy Day dinner, 27 Oct. 1942 (Box 6)
    - War Congress of American Industry, 2 Dec. 1942 (Box 6)
    - Houston Colosseum, Houston, Tex., 21 Dec. 1942 (Box 6)
    - Foreign Press Association, 2 Feb. 1943 (Box 7)
    - Radio statement, 11 Feb. 1943 (Box 7)
    - Mid-Day Luncheon Club, 12 Feb. 1943 (Box 7)
    - Friendly Sons of St. Patrick, 17 Mar. 1943 (Box 7)
    - Graduation of V-7 reserve Midshipmen's School, 31 Mar. 1943
    - Cruiser Vincennes war bond rally, 9 Apr. 1943 (Box 7)
    - Syracuse, N.Y., 17 Apr. 1943 (Box 7)
    - Speech on NBC, 22 Apr. 1943 (Box 7)
    - Radio speech for broadcast in Australia and New Zealand, 25 Apr. 1943 (Box 7)
    - Statement on merchant marine sinkings, 27 Apr. 1943 (Box 7)
    - Speech on CBS, 29 Apr. 1943 (Box 7)
    - Statement to the press, 3 May 1943 (Box 7)
    - Union League Club, 10 May 1943 (Box 7)
    - Massachusetts Committee, Conference of Christians and Jews, 17 May 1943 (Box 7)
    - Commencement at Bethany College, 23 May 1943 (Box 7)
    - Graduation at United States Naval Academy, Annapolis, Md., 9 June 1943 (Box 7)
    - Commencement at Northwestern University, Evanston, Ill., 16 June 1943 (Box 7)
    - Statement before Public Lands Committee, House of Representatives, 25 June 1943 (Box 7)
    - Hollywood Bowl, Hollywood, Calif., 30 June 1943 (Box 7)
    - Inauguration cruiser Los Angeles, 30 June 1943 (Box 7)
    - San Francisco Chamber of Commerce, San Francisco, Calif., 2 July 1943 (Box 7)
    - American Legion Post 1, Seattle, Wash., 5 July 1943 (Box 7)
    - “Report to the Nation” program, CBS, 20 July 1943 (Box 7)
    - Women's Reserve anniversary, Mutual Network, 27 July 1943 (Box 7)
    - Colgate University, Hamilton, N.Y, 28 Aug. 1943 (Box 7)
    - Launching of Hornet, 30 Aug. 1943 (Box 7)
    - Notes for speech on tribute to Downes and Emmet and Great Lakes Station, Aug.-Sept. 1943 (Box 7)
    - Remarks at the "Back the Attack" War Show, 14 Sept. 1943 (Box 7)
    - Soldier voting bill, 21 Oct. 1943 (Box 7)
    - Speech on NBC, 21 Oct. 1943 (Box 7)
    - Philadelphia, Pa., 27 Oct. 1943 (Box 7)
    - Commencement at Williams College, Williamstown, N.Y., Nov. 1943 (Box 7)
    - National Advisory Committee for Aeronautics, 4 Nov. 1943 (Box 7)
    - Press release of Knox letter to Carl Vinson, 23 Nov. 1943 (Box 7)
    - Remarks to Navy Department personnel, 24 Nov. 1943 (Box 7)
    - Statement on navy production in Nov. 1943, 3 Dec. 1943 (Box 7)
    - English Speaking Union, 6 Dec. 1943 (Box 7)
    - Institute of Aeronautical Sciences, 17 Dec. 1943 (Box 7)
    - Christmas message to staff of Navy Department, Dec. 1943 (Box 7)
    - Christmas message to naval personnel and civilians, 24 Dec. 1943 (Box 7)
    - Christmas message to United States Armed Forces, 24 Dec. 1943 (Box 7)
    - Touchdown Club, 11 Jan. 1943 (Box 7)
    - Greater Cleveland Council, Boy Scouts of America, Cleveland, Ohio, 14 Jan. 1944 (Box 7)
    - Opening rally of Red Cross Campaign, Washington, D.C., 1 Mar. 1944 (Box 7)
    - Statement on national service bill before Senate Military Affairs Committee, 2 Mar. 1944 (Box 7)
    - Statement on renewal of lend-lease before House Foreign Affairs Committee, 9 Mar. 1944 (Box 7)
    - Third anniversary of the establishment of United States Naval Base at Bermuda, 6 Apr. 1944 (Box 7)
    - Opening of sixth war loan drive, 13 Apr. 1944 (Box 7)
    - Joint statement of the secretary of war, secretary of the navy, and chairman of the United States Maritime Commission, 20 Apr. 1944 (Box 7)
  - Writings (Box 7)
    - Editorials, Manchester Union Leader, 7 Mar. 1914 (Box 7)
    - The Price of a Managed Economy: A Series of editorials, 1934 (Box 7)
    - Editorials, Chicago Daily News, 1934-1939, (6 folders) (Box 7)
    - “Our Southern Arteries,” Atlantic Monthly, 20 June 1939 (Box 7)
    - Editorials, Chicago Daily News, 1940, 1943, (2 folders) (Box 7)
    - Editorial concerning John Adam Muehling, 20 Apr. 1944 (Box 7)
    - “Let's Train Our Youth Now,” Collier's, 29 Apr. 1944 (Box 7)
- Annie Reid Knox File, 1936-1954 (Box 8-10)
  Letters sent and received by Annie Reid Knox.
  Organized into general correspondence, letters of condolence on the death of Knox to his wife and to James Forrestal, and Cordell Hull, and speeches by Mrs. Knox.
  - General correspondence (Box 8)
    - 1936-1951, (8 folders) (Box 8)
    - 1952-1954, (3 folders) (Box 9)
  - Letters of condolence on death of Frank Knox (Box 9)
    - To Annie Reid Knox, A-Z, (3 folders) (Box 9)
    - To James Forrestal (with replies), A-Z (Box 9)
    - To Cordell Hull (with replies), A-Z (by country) (Box 9)
  - Speeches (Box 10)
    - Alma College, Alma, Mich., 7 Sept. 1936 (Box 10)
    - Men of Hornet, 20 Oct. 1941 (Box 10)
    - American Legion, 1944 (Box 10)
    - Men of Frank Knox, Sept. 1944 (Box 10)
- Miscellany (Box 10-12)
  Memorabilia, miscellaneous business records, passport papers, writings about Knox, clippings, and scrapbooks.
  Arranged by type of material.
  - Miscellaneous documents relating to the death of Knox (Box 10)
  - Documents concerning the commissioning of Frank Knox, 11 Dec. 1944; dedication of Frank Knox recreation room (Box 10)
  - Papers relating to passports for Frank Knox and Annie Reid Knox, 1938-1939 (Box 10)
  - Memorabilia, dinner for Brazilian officers; flags; Navy Day banquet military service, 1898-1940 (Box 10)
  - Miscellaneous business records, 1908-1926 (Box 10)
  - Memorabilia concerning Frank Knox (Box 10)
  - Memorabilia concerning Annie Reid Knox (Box 10)
  - Writings about Frank Knox (Box 10)
  - Clippings (Box 11)
    - 1898-1943, (3 folders) (Box 11)
    - 1944-1953, undated, (7 folders) (Box 12)
  - Scrapbooks See Oversize, (7 vols.) (Box 12)
- Oversize (Box OV 1-7)
  Oversize scrapbooks.
  Arranged and described according to the series and containers from which they were removed.
  - Miscellany (Box OV 1)
    - Scrapbooks (Container 12) (Box OV 1)
      - Biographical (Box OV 1)
      - 1936 presidential campaign (Box OV 2)
      - General, 1940-1944 (Box OV 3)
      - Visit to Brazil, Brazilian newspapers, Oct. 5, 1942, (1 vol.) (Box OV 4, Box OV 5)
      - Death of Knox (Box OV 6)
    - Brazilian newspapers, May 1944 (Box OV 6)
    - General, 1944 (Box OV 7)